by doing this food strike -- we could have gone to jail. But, hey, it worked. Twenty-four hours later, we were picked up from school and escorted to the office of the governor. MW: And there he was -- (Applause) waiting for us to meet and speak, being all supportive and thankful for our willingness to care for the beauty and the environment of Bali. He signed a promise to help the people of Bali say no to plastic bags. And we are now friends, and on a regular basis, we remind him and his team of the promises he has made. And indeed, recently he stated and committed that Bali will be plastic bag free by 2018. (Applause) IW: Also, at the International Airport of Bali, one of our supporters is planning to start a plastic bag-free policy by 2016. MW: Stop handing out free plastic bags and bring in your own reusable bag is our next message to change that mindset of the public. IW: Our short-term campaign, "One Island / One Voice," is all about this. We check and recognize the shops and restaurants that have declared themselves a plastic bag-free zone, and we put this sticker at their entrance and publish their names on social media and some important magazines on Bali. And conversely, that highlights those who do not have the sticker. (Laughter) MW: So, why are we actually telling you all of this? Well, partly, it is because we are proud of the results that, together with our team, we have been able to reach. But also because along the way, we have learned that kids can do things. We can make things happen. Isabel and I were only 10 and 12 years old when we started this. We never had a business plan, nor a fixed strategy, nor any hidden agendas -- just the idea in front of us and a group of friends working with us. All we wanted to do was stop those plastic bags from wrapping and suffocating our beautiful home. Kids have a boundless energy and a motivation to be the change the world needs. IW: So to all the kids of this beautiful but challenging world: go for it! Make that difference. We're not telling you it's going to be easy. We're telling you it's going to be worth it. Us kids may only be 25 percent of the world's population, but we are 100 percent of the future. MW: We still have a lot of work to do, but know that we still not stop until the first question asked when arriving at the Bali airports will be Both: "Welcome to Bali, do you have nay plastic bags to declare?" (Laughter) Om shanti shanti shanti om. Thank you. (Applause)
al hacer esta huelga de hambre, podríamos haber ido a la cárcel. Pero, bueno, funcionó. 24 horas más tarde, nos recogieron en la escuela y nos escoltaron hasta la oficina del gobernador. MW: Y ahí estaba... (Aplausos) esperando vernos para hablar, muy solidario y agradecido por nuestra voluntad de cuidar de la belleza y el medio ambiente de Bali. Él firmó una promesa de ayudar a que la gente de Bali diga no a las bolsas de plástico. Y ahora somos amigos, y de forma regular, le recordamos a él y a su equipo las promesas que nos había hecho. Y, en efecto, recientemente declaró y se comprometió a que Bali estará libre de bolsas de plástico para el año 2018. (Aplausos) IW: En el aeropuerto internacional de Bali, uno de nuestros seguidores tiene la intención de iniciar una política de ausencia de bolsas de plástico en 2016. MW: Detener la entrega de bolsas de plástico gratis y fomentar el traer la propia bolsa reutilizable es nuestro siguiente mensaje para cambiar esa forma de pensar del público. IW: Nuestra campaña a corto plazo, "Una isla / una sola voz" tiene que ver con esto. Comprobamos y reconocemos las tiendas y restaurantes que se han declarado zona libre de bolsas de plástico y ponemos esta etiqueta en su entrada y publicamos sus nombres en las redes sociales y en algunas revistas importantes en Bali. Y, a la inversa, se resaltan aquellos que no tienen la etiqueta. (Risas) MW: Pero ¿por qué le contamos todo esto? Bueno, en parte, porque estamos orgullosas de los resultados que, junto con nuestro equipo, hemos podido lograr. Y también porque en el camino, hemos aprendido que los niños pueden hacer cosas. Podemos hacer que las cosas sucedan. Isabel y yo solo teníamos 10 y 12 años cuando empezamos esto. Nunca tuvimos un plan de negocios, ni una estrategia fija, ni agendas ocultas. Solo la idea y un grupo de amigos que trabajan con nosotras. Todo lo que queríamos era evitar que esas bolsas de plástico se enrollaran y sofocaran nuestra hermosa casa. Los niños tienen una energía sin límites y una motivación para ser el cambio que el mundo necesita. IW: Así que para todos los niños de este hermoso pero desafiante mundo: ¡vayan a por ello! Marquen la diferencia. Nosotros no decimos que vaya a ser fácil. Decimos que valdrá la pena. Nosotros los niños solo somos el 25 % de la población mundial, pero seremos el 100 % del futuro. MW: Todavía tenemos mucho trabajo por hacer, pero sabemos que no nos detendremos hasta que la primera pregunta que hizo al llegar a los aeropuertos de Bali sea Ambas: "Bienvenidos a Bali, ¿tienen alguna bolsa de plástico para declarar?" (Risas) Om Shanti Shanti Shanti Om. Gracias. (Aplausos)